Mai-chan, let's go home together!
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）麻衣(まい)ちゃん
一緒に帰ろう
（水上(みなかみ)麻衣）
防火水そう
寄っていい？
Can I stop by a fire hydrant?
Now, now, that's no place for a school girl to go!
またまた　女子高生の
寄る所じゃないじゃん
Oh, that's right, Mai-chan.
（祐子）
あっ そうそう 麻衣ちゃん
Do you want to stop by Daiku Coffee?
帰りに 大工(だいく)コーヒー寄ってく？
システムなんかが
結構 変わっちゃってて―
They changed the system quite a bit in there,
麻衣ちゃんには ちょっと
難しいかもしれないから
so it may be a bit difficult for you, Mai-chan.
よいしょっ
But I can teach you all about it.
私がいろいろ教えてあげる
Oh, Mai-chan...
ま… 麻衣ちゃん
That's...
それ…
Asymmetry.
アシンメトリー
Well, that's true and all,
いやっ そうだけど
ゆゆしき非対称だよ
but that's beyond the intended purpose or fashion!
おしゃれのＫ点
越えちゃってるよ
I was just being dumb.
ボケたんだけど
That's way over the top.
（祐子）全力投球すぎるよ
Mai-chan, from left to right, everything is just messed up!
麻衣ちゃん
何がなにやら もう―
とっちらかっちゃってるよ
But I guess that's just Mai-chan's way.
天は 麻衣ちゃんの味方なんだね
（阪本(さかもと)の寝息）
（東雲(しののめ)なの）うーん
Nichijou 68
What should I do for today's menu?
今日の献立
何にしようかなあ
ネギが安いらしいから
ネギ料理かな
I heard green onions were on sale, so maybe something with that?
But Professor doesn't like green onions.
でも はかせ
ネギ嫌いだからなあ
Nano! Nano!
（はかせ）
なの！ なの なのっ
Nano!
わあっ！
Look, Nano!
なの 見て　カラス捕まえた
I caught a crow.
Good heavens!
（なの）なんてこったあ
（なの）
…って 何やってるんですか
What are you doing?
That's dangerous!
危ないですって
つつかれますよ
You'll get pecked!
It's fine. Just wait a moment.
大丈夫　ちょっと待ってて
（阪本）ニャアー ニャアッ
It wasn't there.
（阪本）無かったか
（阪本）ニャアウ ニャウ ニャウ
ニャン ニャウ ニャアアウ
ニャア ニャアッ ニャアッ
I might die.
（阪本）死ぬかも
（阪本）ニャアウウッ
ニャアアウ
ニャアウ ニャアウ
（阪本）ハアッ ここも違うか
It's not here, either.
いつの間にかスカーフが
なくなりやがった
My scarf suddenly disappeared.
Hello.
（カラス）どうも カラスです
I'm a crow.
Pleased to make your acquaintance.
（カラス）以後 お見知り置きを
（阪本）ギャフン！
It's a good thing this is a well-mannered crow.
礼儀正しいカラスで
よかったですね
That's because it's a crow.
カラスだから
I am honoured to receive your praise.
（カラス）
お褒めに預かり光栄です
I wonder if it'll drink strawberry milk.
（はかせ）
イチゴ牛乳 飲むかなあ？
飲みますかねえ？
You think so?
（はかせ）飲んだらカワイイね
It would be cute if it did!
（カラス）はっ！
（なの）キャアッ！ うっ
A mosquito...
（なの）蚊？
Unbelievable.
なんと…
For it to exterminate bugs!
虫退治してくれるなんて
いや なに
当然のことをしたまでです
Well, it was the natural thing to do.
カラスだなあ
He's quite a crow.
（阪本）
ニャウ ニャウ ニャウウウッ
Oh, Sakamoto-san, where's your scarf?
あれっ？ 阪本さん
スカーフどうしたんですか？
I can't tell what he's saying without his scarf.
スカーフないと
何言ってっか分かんないね
（カラス）私が聞きましょう
I shall ask him.
（阪本）ニャアウッ ニャウッ
（阪本）ニャアウ ニャウニャウ
（カラス）フム フムフム
（阪本）ニャアウ
I see.
なるほど なるほど
（阪本）ニャウ ニャウウ
It seems that he wants my scarf.
どうやら
私のスカーフが欲しいようですね
なるほど
I see.
It's not yours!
（阪本）お前のじゃねえだろ！
Professor, did you put Sakamoto-san's scarf on the crow?
はかせ
もしかして阪本さんのスカーフを
カラスに着けたんですか？
エヘヘ
Oh my, how terrible of me.
いやはや 面目無い
（なの）
うーん でも それじゃあ
阪本さんがかわいそうですよ
Well, if that's so, then I feel bad for Sakamoto-san.
I'll go make another one!
分かった　作ってくる
That would be nice.
（カラス）それがいいですね
It's done!
出来たあ！
Biscuit #1.
“ビスケット１号”です
（阪本）スカーフ関係ねえ
That's not a scarf at all!
By the way, Professor, what kinds of abilities does Biscuit #1 have?
（カラス）時に はかせ
ビスケット１号には―
どんな機能が
ついているのですか？
カラス　いいこと言った
That's a very good question, Crow.
He has a rocket punch.
ロケットパンチがついています
Here we go!
じゃ いくよ
Ready! Set!
せーの
Launch!
発射！ ピコー！
（なの･はかせ･カラス）
ウッハハハハッ アハハッ
は… はかせ
Professor, you should get on with making a scarf for Sakamoto-san.
そろそろ阪本さんに
ス… スカーフを　フフフ
Wait a second.
ちょっと 待って
After all, there's still the left hand!
なぜなら まだ左手があるから
Ready! Set!
せーの
発射！ ピコー！
Launch!
（阪本）ニャア！
Shinonome Institute
Kill.
（阪本）殺す　こいつら殺す
I'm going to kill these guys.
My, I had a wonderful day today.
（カラス）いやあ
今日は本当に楽しかった
I might have been too mean.
私も 悪ふざけが過ぎたようですね
Please give this scarf back to Sakamoto-san.
この スカーフは―
阪本さんに
返してあげてください
Even if it was just for a short while,
ほんのひとときでも―
I was happy to be able to speak the words of a human.
人間の言葉をしゃべれて
うれしかったです
Crow...
カラス
あっ 行かないで　カラス
Don't leave, Crow!
Professor!
はかせ
I hope we'll be able to meet again.
（カラス）また機会があれば
お会いしましょう
Well then, I bid you good day.
それでは 皆さん　お達者で
See you again!
シー ユー アゲイン！
Crow!
（はかせ）カラス！
Crow...
（阪本）カラス
He took it with him!
持っていきやがったあ！
Love-Like
I can't do it, Manager!
（男性社員）無理ですよ 課長
No, it's all right.
（課長）
いいや 大丈夫だ　俺に任せろ
Just leave it to me.
（男性社員）ですが
But...
What?
（課長）
なんだ？ 俺が信用できないのか
You can't trust me?
（男性社員）
いやっ そういうわけでは
That's not it...
I trust you completely, Manager.
（男性社員）課長を
全面的に信用しています
（課長）
よしっ　ならば私に手を貸せ
All right... Give me a hand, then.
（男性社員）あっ いや あっ
あいたたたっ 痛い痛い痛い
（課長）どう？ 効いてる？
Well? How is it?
どうなのよ
Nichijou 69
Go Slowly
Behind the Gymnasium 1
Yesterday, I dug a trap behind the gymnasium.
（中村(なかむら)先生）
昨日 体育館裏に掘った
接着剤入り落し穴
It's filled with Super Glue.
High
Strength
Super      Glue
I'll lure her there with this letter and trap her.
この手紙で呼び寄せて
ワナにはめてやる
High
Strength
Shinonome Nano
I shall capture you today, Shinonome Nano.
今日こそ捕獲してやるぞ 東雲なの
うんん？
She's here!
来たっ！
All right!
（中村）よしっ
（中村）うんん
（中之条 剛(なかのじょうつよし)）おほっ おほっ
おわああ！
（桜井 誠(さくらいまこと)）えっ
（高崎(たかさき)先生）まさか 桜井誠が
桜井先生の弟だったとはな
I can't believe that Sakurai Makoto was Sakurai-sensei's brother.
Nichijou 70
I should find a way to get information about Sakurai-sensei from him.
どうにかして―
桜井先生の情報を
聞き出さないと
That kid...
（高崎）あいつ…
He can play Go Soccer!?
囲碁サッカーできるのか
Interesting.
面白い
Hey, Sakurai.
（高崎）おい！ 桜井
（誠）あっ はい
Yeah?
Does she have a boyfriend?
今 つきあっている彼氏は
いるんですか？
No future!
ノー フューチャー！
（高崎）いつも こうだ
俺って男は 俺って男は…
It's always like this!
I'm terrible!
Well, no, but...
ええっと いませんけど
（誠）
いませんけど いませんけど
Here it comes!
ほいきたあ
Oh no! This can't be!
ほい きてねえっ  ほい きてねえ
（誠）あの
（高崎）ほっ！
Excuse me...
（高崎）すまん すまん
今のは 水に流してくれ
Sorry about that.
Just forget about it.
そうだ  お前　囲碁サッカー
やってるのか？
Oh, right: you play Go Soccer?
I do.
やってますけど
Sensei, could it be...
もしかして 先生―
...that you like my sister?
うちの姉ちゃん　好きでしょ？
かああ…
What are you saying?!
バカ言ってんじゃないよ！
I'm just your senior as a Go Soccer player!
俺はただ 囲碁サッカー部の
先輩としてだな
えっ？ 先生 囲碁サッカー
やってたんですか？
Sensei, you played Go Soccer?
Of course!
あったぼうよ！
これでも
高校ＭＶＰだったんだぞ
I may not look like it, but I was actually the MVP in high school!
ああ 先生　実は今―
Sensei, our Go Soccer club doesn't have an advisor.
うちの囲碁サッカー部には
顧問がいないんです
If you become our advisor, I'd completely assist you with my sister!
もし 顧問に
なってくれるんだったら―
うちの姉ちゃんのこと
全面協力しますよ
ハッ 俺は だからべつに
好きってわけじゃ
Like I said, it's not like I like her or anything...
If you don't become our advisor, I'll tell my sister that you like her.
顧問になってくれないなら―
先生が姉ちゃんのこと好きって
言いふらします
ちょっ お前
Why, you!
Well, which is it?
（誠）どうなんですか？
顧問になるんですか？
Will you become our advisor?
あの…
Or won't you?
（誠）ならないんですか？
えっと いや…
Well... Being an advisor seems like a lot of work.
だが しかし
顧問は 面倒くさ…
Hey, guys!
（誠）
おーい みんな　聞いてくれ
Listen up!
Don't move!
（高崎）ゴナムーブ
（高崎）お… 追うぞ
I've gotta go after him!
Sensei!
（安中(あんなか)）先生！
Takanojou-kun is stuck in a hole behind the gymnasium!
体育館裏で 中之条君が
埋まっちゃってるんですけど
Eh!?
I need you to come immediately.
（安中）すぐ来てほしいですけど
（高崎）えっ
（誠）おーい　高崎先生が…
Hey, Takasaki-sensei is...
Sensei!
（安中）先生！
（高崎）あっ
All right, listen closely.
いいか よく聞け
（安中）はい
All right!
Nakanojou is...
（高崎）
中之条は 埋まっていない
...not stuck!
Yeah, it could be a hole in one!
そうだ
ホールインワンかもしれん
Also, his hair has come off!
しかも 髪の毛が
抜けてるんですけど
（高崎）ええ！　書き込め
Draw it on.
（安中）ええ！ やってみます
I'll try.
（高崎）
ええ！ ちょっと 待て
Hold on!
What about that?
あれは どういうことなんだ？
Hey! Tea...
（誠）おーい お茶
I think it's more important to prevent someone from revealing another's private affairs...
埋まってるよりも―
他人のプライベートを
暴露する生徒を―
...than to worry about a student in a hole, because a teacher is...
取り締まるほうが
教育者としての―
何だ その… 教育者だ！
Because that's what it means to be a teacher!
高崎先生
Takasaki-sensei!
（高崎）はいっ！
（誠）言ってませんよ
Yes!
I won't say anything.
Also, I'm waiting for you to become our advisor!
それより 顧問　待ってまーす
Way to go.
超 こいつ
Annaka, let's go!
安中！ 行くぞ
はいっ！
Okay!
（高崎）急いで行くぜっ
Let's hurry!
That's what it means to be a teacher.
それが 教師ってもんだろ
（安中）こっちです
It's this way!
（高崎）こっちか
This way?
（中村）
さすがに 勢いとはいえ
I guess I got a little ahead of myself.
I feel bad about cutting his hair.
髪 刈っちゃったのは
悪かったな
I guess I'll go save him.
助けてやるか
Behind the Gymnasium 2
He probably has no idea that I'm the culprit.
私が やったなど
やつには分からないしな
What?
（高崎）何だ
（安中）あれっ？
Huh?
What is this?
（高崎）何だこれ どこだ？
（安中）あれれ？ あれ？
Huh?
What is this?
Something's wrong!
（高崎）ここはどこだ？ 変だ
（安中）あれれ あれ？ あれ？
What is this?
（高崎）何だこれ 動けんぞ
（安中）あれれ？ えっと
I can't move!
Huh?
My hair...
What?
（高崎）何だ？ 何だ何だ何だ？
（中之条）髪が…
What, what, what?
（中村）逃げろ
Run away!
（安中）助けてえ
（中之条）髪が…
Help me!
My hair...
Swim, Swim,
（なの･はかせ）♪ すい すい
Sharky, Sharky, Chomp!
（なの）♪ サメ サメ パクッ
（はかせ）♪ サメ サメ パクッ
If that happens, do this!
（なの･はかせ）
♪ それなら これ何だ？
Chicchi is like this!
（チッチ）ニャアウ
ニャアーウ
ニャウウ
（ドアが開く音）
（祐子）いってきまーす
I'm heading out now!
（祐子）今日こそ
Today, I definitely won't respond!
Nichijou 71
ツッコんで
あげないんだからっ
It's all Mai-chan's fault.
（祐子）元はといえば
麻衣ちゃんが 悪いんだよ
She's always fooling around,
機械のようにボケまくって
いっつもいつも 私がツッコんで
and I'm always responding to it!
At this rate, it'll be an endless loop of jokes and responses!
このままじゃ
ボケとツッコミの―
イタチループ！
We're supposed to be pure enough to put flowers to shame!
私たちは 乙女
そう　花も恥じらう
乙女だったはず
And yet...
それなのに―
I can't even have a normal conversation like a high school girl.
普通の女子高生みたいな会話も
できないんだもん
From now on, I'm not going to respond to anything!
今日から 絶対ツッコまないぞ
My resolve is harder than diamond.
私の意志は―
ダイヤモンドよりも
固いんだから
Oh, Yukko, good morning.
（麻衣）あっ ゆっこ　おはよう
Oh, Mai-chan, good mor-
（祐子）
ああ 麻衣ちゃん　おは…
Double glasses!
ダブル眼鏡！
This is strong.
強烈だ！ 今日は強烈だ
今日にかぎって 強烈だ！
Unlike the other days, today is strong!
But I won't give in!
だけど 負けない！
私は… 私たちは
変わるんだから！
Because I will... We will change!
Mai-chan, selamat pagi!
麻衣ちゃん　スラマッパギー
All right, now is the time to engage in some flowery girls' talk.
（祐子）よし！ 今こそ
ガールズトークに花咲かせるとき
Hey, Mai-chan, did you watch Muscle Elegy yesterday?
ねえねえ 麻衣ちゃん
昨日の「筋肉挽歌(きんにくばんか)」見た？
W-Which one?!
（祐子）
ど… どどどっち？
Where are my glasses?
眼鏡 眼鏡
（祐子）オンギャアア！
な… 何 このハイペースなボケ
This is some rapid-fire stupidity!
まるで 私のツッコミを
待っているかのような
It's like she's waiting for me to respond!
No!
ダメ！ ツッコんではダメよ
ゆっこ これはワナ！
You must not respond, Yukko!
This is a trap!
（田中(たなか)）あれっ？ なんだよ 水上
２個も眼鏡してんじゃん
What's wrong, Minakami?
You've got two pairs of glasses on!
（祐子）ふっ！ 田中の野郎
Tanaka, you bastard!
私のツッコミを―
He took my response!
The response that only I can make!
私だけに許された
最高のツッコミを！
No, wait. It's not mine.
いや 違う違う 私んじゃない
That wasn't my response.
それは 私のツッコミじゃないから
Oh, right.
あっ そうだ
今日の１時限目 国語だっけ？
First period today is Language.
Yeah, I heard Nakamura, the science teacher, collapsed again.
（祐子）そうだよ
そういえば 理科の中村
倒れたらしいね
Oh, I wonder if she's all right.
（麻衣）へえ 大丈夫かな
Oh, right.
あっ そうだ
今日の１時限目 国語だっけ？
First period today is Language.
No, you just said th-
（祐子）
いや それさっき言っ…
That was close!
（祐子）あっぶな！
Why did she say the same thing twice?!
この子　同じセリフ
なんで２回言ったの？
That was frightening!
末恐ろしい
末恐ろしいわ この子！
This girl is frightening!
（学校のチャイム）
（高崎）よーし 日直  号令
All right, everyone stand up.
Stand.
（麻衣）起立　礼
Bow.
Take your seed.
着せこ
All right, I'll begin the lesson.
じゃあ 授業を始めるぞ
Open to page 82.
Take your "seed"...
（祐子）“着せこ”って…
What does that even mean?!
着せこって何なんだよ
Everyone ignored it!
しかも 全員 総スルーかよ
Would anyone like to read?
じゃあ 読みたいやつはいるか？
Here.
（麻衣）はい
（祐子）ああっ！
（祐子）
ま… 麻衣ちゃあん！
M-Mai-chan!
じゃあ 水上
All right, Minakami.
Okay.
（麻衣）はい
Silence surrounded the mountain as it began getting dark.
（麻衣）山は静かに…
（祐子）し… しかも
読んでるってことは
The fact that she's actually reading it means...
A natural calamity struck us from behind.
From the place where our journey began...
If she's actually reading it, then it means...
読んでるってことは―
It means...
ことは―
ことは！
You memorised it all!?
（祐子）丸暗記かよ！
Responding...
（祐子）
やっぱ ツッコミって
...feels...
超―
...really wonderful!
気持ちいい！
I'm sorry for shouting!
大声出して すいませんでした
ハア
I'll go stand in the hall!
廊下に立ってます
Yes.
（祐子）そう これでいいの
It's fine this way.
This is my path,
これが 私の道だから
and...
そして―
これが 麻衣ちゃんの道だもの
...this is Mai-chan's path.
Yukko.
（麻衣）ゆっこ
（祐子）うん
The truth is...
（麻衣）実は 今朝から―
...I've been wearing contacts all morning.
コンタクト
The glasses had no purpose!
眼鏡 意味ないじゃんっ！
Shinonome Institute
Kotatsu
Professor, that's not good.
はかせ はかせ　ダメですよ
If you don't sleep in your futon, you'll catch a cold.
ちゃんと お布団で寝ないと
カゼひきますよ
Come on, Professor.
はかせってば
もう ちょっとだから
Just a bit longer.
えっ？ もうちょっと？
Just a bit longer?
（はかせ）ふーん
I've been had!
やられたっ！
（はかせ）ふうう
（なの）よっこいしょっと
Sakamoto-san.
阪本さん
Sakamoto-san, you should go to your bed, too.
阪本さんも
お布団にいきますよ
（阪本）うん おう
In the end, she'll bring it along.
I'm the three of spades!
（スペードの３）
スペードの３だ
I may be the weakest in Daifugou,
大富豪なら最弱の俺だが―
but if there's a reversion, I suddenly become the strongest!
革命が起きると
一気に最強になれるんだっ
If you're a man, you have to aim for that!
男だったら
下克上を狙わないとな
Next time on Nichijou: Episode 18.
次回の「日常」は
第18話
Narration:     Nakai Kazuya
Look forward to it!
お楽しみに